<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaration and propositions of the navie with the oath which they have taken, concerning an admirall for the seas, and who they made choice of for the present. A message from the Kentish-men to the Lord Generall, and his answer thereunto. A thousand of them come in, and Dover Fort taken. With the taking of Chepstow Castle by storme, the Governour Sir Nicholas Kemish, and others slain; with the number of officers and prisoners taken. As also another petition to the Parliament, from the City of London, and what is desired therein.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82076</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D58</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E445_32</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204795</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864256</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864256</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161762</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82076)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161762)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 70:E445[32])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaration and propositions of the navie with the oath which they have taken, concerning an admirall for the seas, and who they made choice of for the present. A message from the Kentish-men to the Lord Generall, and his answer thereunto. A thousand of them come in, and Dover Fort taken. With the taking of Chepstow Castle by storme, the Governour Sir Nicholas Kemish, and others slain; with the number of officers and prisoners taken. As also another petition to the Parliament, from the City of London, and what is desired therein.</title>
                  <author>M. D.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 3, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Alsop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A letter from Sandwich in Kent" is dated and signed: Sandwich 28. May, 1648. Your assured friend, M. D.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 1st".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Royal Navy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Royalists --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Naval operations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Kent (England) --  History --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161762:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 124 -->
            <p>THE DECLARATION AND PROPOSITIONS OF THE NAVIE With the Oath which they have taken, concerning an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall for the Seas, and who they made choice of for the preſent.</p>
            <p>A Meſſage from the Kentiſh-men to the Lord Generall, and his Anſwer thereunto. A thouſand of them come in, and <hi>Dover</hi> Fort taken.</p>
            <p>With the taking of <hi>Chepstow</hi> Caſtle by ſtorme, the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Sir <hi>Nicholas Kemiſh,</hi> and others ſlain; with the number of Officers and priſoners taken.</p>
            <p>As alſo another Petition to the Parliament, from the City of <hi>London, and what is deſired therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>B. Alſop,</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:161762:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 125 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161762:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 125 -->
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>A LETTER From <hi>Sandwich</hi> in KENT:</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>FOr the prevention of falſe informations, I ſhall communicate to you the moſt certain intelligence we have in theſe parts. <hi>On Fryday laſt Vice-admirall</hi> Rainsborough <hi>came aſhore at his owne Caſtle at</hi> Deale, <hi>the occaſion was, becauſe ſome of the Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh men had endeavoured to get the poſſeſſion of the Earl of</hi> Warwicks <hi>Caſtle of</hi> Sandon, <hi>the caſtle of</hi> Warbrough, <hi>and this Caſtle, which are all three
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161762:3"/>
                        <!-- PDF PAGE 126 -->within a mile and a half one of the other.</hi> And when the Vice Admirall had done his endeavour to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them he went in a ſmall Pinace to his command a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain at <hi>Sea;</hi> and when he came to the ſhip which was under his immediate command, thoſe which were in her forbad him to come aboard, ſaying they would obey him no longer, but would have the King brought to London, &amp;c and told him if he came aboard, it was at his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill, but if he pleaſed, he might depart in the Veſsel hee was in, and after many threats, and other uncivil car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages towards him, he came for London; when hee was gone, they hung forth a flag, which ſignified, that there ſhould be a Councel held, and the reſpective Captaines in all other ſhips, were to appear aboard on the Vice ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral, and divers of them met accordingly, but Captain <hi>Penroſe</hi> came not. Whereupon they ſent him three or four Canon ſhot, and afterwards ſent a meſsage to him, commanding him, in the name of the Vice admirall, to come to the Councell: whereupon he returned anſwer that he knew the Vice-admirall was not there, and therefore conceived, they had not power to call a Councell, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand him to come thither, and therefore hee was reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not to go.</p>
                  <p>This Meſsage was carryed back, and upon the receit thereof, about <hi>40.</hi> men went with their ſwords drawne,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161762:3"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 126 -->and other weapons of war, came to him in another ſhip, and told him, that they were ſent by the Admirall to fet him. Captain <hi>Penroſe</hi> asked who was that Vice admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, they replyed, that his name was <hi>Lenoall:</hi> then captain <hi>Penroſe</hi> ſaid, he knew ſuch a man to bee a Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtons Mate, but no otherwiſe, and was reſolved not to go with them; then ſaid they, we muſt force you: the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain now addreſſed his ſpeech to his owne men in the ſhip ſaying, <hi>Gentlemen, will you ſtick to me, and we will defend our ſelves, and not obey this ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall command;</hi> but contrary to his expectation, hee found a diviſion amongſt his own men, and many of them cryed out, <hi>Go, go,</hi> this being ſo, captaine <hi>Penroſe</hi> for the better prevention of further miſchief, went along with them, and when he came aboard the Vice admiral, he was d<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed to ſign a Petition, which he refuſed to do, and finding him whom they for the preſent, h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d choſen to be Vice Admirall, to be this inferiour man, which was but a Bostons mate.</p>
                  <p>Capt. <hi>Penroſe</hi> ſaid, I will not joine with you in this Petition no<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> approve of your courſe in refuſing to be commanded by the Vice-Admirall which was put in by the Parliament.</p>
                  <p>And, I pray, do you quite caſt off all ſubjection to them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:161762:4"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 127 -->
to which they generally replyed no, they were for King and Parliament: then ſaid he, it were fit that you ſhould mrke choice of ſome honourable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that is true to both, for this is a place not fit for any other, &amp;c. hee had no ſooner ſpoken this, but one of them named the Earl of <hi>Warwick,</hi>and all the reſt cryed out preſently, <hi>a Warwick, a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick:</hi> then they agreed to ſend a Letter to his Lordſhip, &amp; another to the Speaker of the houſe, ſetting forth their proceedings, and that if the E. of 
<hi> Warwick</hi> came to them, they would live and dy with him, in defence of the cauſe for King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, according to the firſt principles; and they made choice of capt. <hi>Penroſe</hi> to bring theſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp; before his coming away, he told them, that it might be when he was gone, they would make choice of ſome other; and to give ſatisfaction to the contrary, they all took an oath, not to receed from this choice untill the E. of <hi>Warwick</hi>came to them, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>On Fryday laſt the Kentiſh men took the Fort neer <hi>Dover</hi> Caſtle, whereof capt. <hi>Bethel,</hi> a very de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving Gentleman, had the command, they ſhot many pieces againſt the Caſtle, but finding no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability of doing any good againſt it, they gave it over, which is all at preſent, from</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Sandwich <date>28 May, 1648.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your aſſured friend, <hi>M. D.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:161762:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 127 -->
               <hi>May</hi> 29, the Parliament taking into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion this buſines of the Navy, and voted the E. of <hi>Warwick</hi> to be Admiral; wherevpon his Lordſhip took his journy thither on <hi>Tueſday</hi> morning: the <hi>Parl.</hi> debated on a letter which they received out of <hi>Kent,</hi> and paſſed a vote, that the buſines concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their taking up of arms ſhould bee referred to the L. Gen. and as for that part of their petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, concerning the King, the houſe will doe that therein, which ſhall ſatisfy them and the whole Kingdom: whereupon his Excellency with a bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of horſe and foot, marched this 30. of <hi>May</hi> to Black-heath, where the Kentiſh-men ſaid they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to keep their Randevouz, who at ſight re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated to a Village, lining the hedges with muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quetiers, and preſently after ſent a trumpeter to the Gen. deſiring a teeaty; but the anſwer was, he would ſend an anſwer by a meſſeng<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r of his owne. About 12. of the clock the ſame day ca<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e letters to the <hi>Parl.</hi> that 1000. of the Kentiſh men were come in to the Gen. with their arms, which they laid down to him, and declared, that they were deeply ſenſible of the errours they had committed, &amp;c. the re<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t of the Kentiſh men are retreated back to <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and deſire a treaty by way of pacifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:161762:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 128 -->
A Capt. brought Letters to the houſe the 29 of <hi>May,</hi> certifiing that Chepſtow Caſtle was taken on Thurſday laſt the manner thus, thoſe in the Caſtle Wedneſday, the 26 of <hi>May,</hi> hung forth a white flag deſired a parley which was granted, at which parley thoſe in the Caſtle, ſtood for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and upon tearms, which were denied on the other part So the parley was ſoone over and when it was taken of Lievtenant Generall Cromwells men ſtormed it, and by their batteries made a large breach at which they entred and upon their for approach the ſouldiers called quarter which was granted, but Sir Nicolas Kemiſh the Governour refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take any, and by that meanes ended his dayes there. There were 21 priſoners taken about, 20 Officers, and 150 Armes, the Capt. which brought the newes, and did good ſervice in the action had 50 l. given him for his paines and charges in this journey.</p>
            <p>Tueſday <hi>May</hi> 30 A Petition was preſented to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon councell of the City of <hi>London,</hi> ſubſcribed by many perſons of quallity, the ſaid City deſiring the approbation of that honourable Court to a Petition to the honourable houſes of Parliament, praying that there may be a preſent treaty with the kings Majeſty, and that for the better ſafety of the Parliament City and peace of the Kingdome there may be an aſſociation of the City and ſeverall Counties ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent, which petition was approved of and, ordered to be preſented to the Parliament at the next opportunity.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gilbert Mabbott.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
